<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon ad clerum at the visitation of the deane and chapter there, holden the 19th day of November, anno Dom. 1662 : by the Most Reverend Father in God Acceptus, by Divine Providence Lord Arch-Bishop of York his Grace, Primate of England and Metropolitan / preacht by Thomas Bradley ...</title>
            <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29122</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4137</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36506</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15713902</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15713902</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104483</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29122)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104483)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1179:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon ad clerum at the visitation of the deane and chapter there, holden the 19th day of November, anno Dom. 1662 : by the Most Reverend Father in God Acceptus, by Divine Providence Lord Arch-Bishop of York his Grace, Primate of England and Metropolitan / preacht by Thomas Bradley ...</title>
                  <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Stephen Bulkley, and are to be sold by Francis Mawbarne ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Yorke :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation II, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:104483:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>COncionem banc perlegi, &amp; cùm nihil in eâ aut Eccleſiae Anglicanae, aut bonis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus contrarium reperiatur, Publicâ Luce do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandam cenſui.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Edm. Diggle, S. T. P. <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendiſsime in Chriſto Patri, ac Dom'. Dom'. Archiepiſc',</hi> Eborac. <hi>à Sacris Domeſt.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Datum,</hi> Epiſcopo-Thorpae, <date>16. Calend. Septem 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:104483:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON AD CLERUM: At the Viſitation of the DEANE and CHAPTER there, holden the 19th. day of <hi>November, Anno Dom.</hi> 1662.</p>
            <p>By the moſt Reverend Father in God ACCEPTUS By Divine Providence, Lord Arch-Biſhop of YORK his GRACE, Primate of <hi>England</hi> and Metropolitan.</p>
            <p>Preacht by <hi>Thomas Bradley, D. D.</hi> one of his late Majeſties Chaplains, and Praebendary of the Church afore-ſaid.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Canſt thou ſtay the ſweet influences of the Pleades? or looſe the bands of Orion,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Job 38.31.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
               <p>The Sauffers, and the Snuffe-diſhes, ſhall be of pure Gold,
<bibl>
                     <hi>Exod. 25.38.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Yorke,</hi> Printed by <hi>Stephen Bulkley,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Francis Mawbarne</hi> at the Minſter-Gates, 1663.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum Privilegio.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:104483:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104483:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Revel. 2.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And to the Angel of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Write, Theſe things ſaith he, which holdeth the ſeven Starrs in his right hand, and walketh in the midſt of the ſeven golden Candleſticks.</p>
                  <p>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Ver. 2.</hi>
                     </bibl> I know thy Works, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the precedent Chapter, we have the Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a wonderfull Perſon, <hi>One like unto the Son of Man, walking in the midſt of ſeven Golden Candleſticks, clothed with a garment down to the foot, and girt about the paps with a Golden Girdle,</hi> ver. 13. <hi>His head and his haire as white as wooll, or ſnow, and his eyes as a flame of fire,</hi> ver. 14. <hi>And his feet as fiue braſſe, burning in a furnace: and his voyce as the ſound of many waters,</hi> ver. 15. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which is none other, but the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the Eternall Sonne of God, in his glorious capacities of <hi>King, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Prophet</hi> of his Church. In theſe two Chapters, the ſecond and the third, are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained ſeven Epiſtles, written from him to the ſeven famous Churches of <hi>Aſia:</hi> To every Epiſtle there is prefixt a ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Preface; and every of thoſe Prefaces taken out of ſome part of that glorious deſcription: As for inſtance; The Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to this firſt Epiſtle, is taken out of thoſe parts of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription which are found, <hi>verſes</hi> 13. <hi>and</hi> 16. Verſe the 13. <hi>I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104483:3"/>ſaw one like unto the Sonne of Man in the midſt of the ſeven golden Candleſticks:</hi> And in the 16. ver. <hi>He had in his right hand ſeven Starrs,</hi> thus the Deſcription: The Preface to the Epiſtle thus, <hi>Thus ſaith he, which holdeth in his right hand the ſeven Starrs, and walketh in the midſt of the ſeven golden Candleſticks.</hi> The Preface of the Epiſtle to the ſecond Church, the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> is taken out of thoſe parts of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription which are found <hi>ver.</hi> 11. and the 18. <hi>ver.</hi> the 11. thus, <hi>I am the firſt and the laſt:</hi> And <hi>ver.</hi> the 18. thus, <hi>I was dead, and am alive,</hi> thus the Deſcription; the preface to the Epiſtle thus: <hi>Thus ſaith he which is the firſt and the laſt, which was dead, and is alive;</hi> and ſo of the reſt: The Preface to every one of them is taken out of ſuch part of this glorious Deſcription, as repreſents Chriſt unto them in ſuch a forme or poſture, as is moſt ſuitable to that Churches State, or Condition, ſuch as may adde a greater authority to the whole Epiſtle, ſuch as may make the deeper impreſſion into them, and procure the greater reverence and obedience to that which is written and contained in them. But our buſineſſe is with the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the moſt famous of all the reſt; Famous for this, that it was the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis of all the reſt; <hi>Epheſus</hi> was the Metropolis of all <hi>Aſia:</hi> Famous for the Univerſity there, it was an Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as <hi>Atheus</hi> was, but it ſeems they ſtudied much the black Art; for when by the Preaching of St. <hi>Paul</hi> among them, they were convinced of the vanity of thoſe Studies, in teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their Repentance, <hi>They brought their Conjuring Books, and burnt them before all men,</hi> but firſt they were pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, and upon the valuation, <hi>they came to fifty thouſand pieces of ſilver,</hi> Acts 19. Famous for the magnificent Temple of <hi>Diana,</hi> in it the ſtatelyeſt Fabrique in the world, two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and twenty years in building, as ſome Hiſtories relate;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104483:3"/>Famous for the Preaching of St. <hi>Paul</hi> there, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. and for that Divine Epiſtle which he Wrote to that Church, inſerted in the ſacred Canon, and one of the largeſt among them, the Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians;</hi> But much more famous for this Epiſtle written unto them, more immediately from our Lord himſelf, whereof our Text is a part: Other Churches had the Honour to be written unto by the holy Apoſtles of our Lord: but this, more immediately by our Lord himſelf; for he it is which here dictates to his ſacred Penman, and amanuenſis, <hi>John, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church of</hi> Epheſus <hi>Write.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So then, It was St. <hi>Johns</hi> Charge to write this Epiſtle; It is our Buſineſſe now to Reade it, and to conſider of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of it: For not unto <hi>Epheſus</hi> alone; but unto us doth it belong, <hi>Let him that hath an eare, heare what the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches:</hi> To us therefore, as directly doth it belong, as if the Epiſtle were ſuperſcribed, To the Angel of the Church of <hi>York,</hi> write, <hi>Theſe things ſaith he, that holdeth the ſeven Starrs in his right hand, and walketh in the midſt of the ſeven golden Candleſticks:</hi> Novi opera tua, <hi>I know thy works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the opening of this Letter, at the firſt view, it divides it ſelf into theſe three Parts:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Perſon to whom it is directed here, repreſented to us under the name and Notion of an Angel, <hi>To the Angel of the Church of</hi> Epheſus.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The deſcription of the Perſon, from whom it is ſent, as he is here repreſented to us in two wonderfull poſtures; 1. <hi>Holding in his right hand ſeven Stars.</hi> 2. <hi>Walking in the midſt of the ſeven golden Candleſticks; Theſe things ſaith he, which, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſpeciall notice that he took of their ſtate and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104483:4"/>condition, the carriage and behaviour of that Church, in theſe words, <hi>Novi opera tua, I know thy works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, oh for the Tongue of an Angel, to ſpeak of ſo Angelicall, ſo Heavenly a ſubject, <hi>Angels, Starrs, Golden Candleſticks!</hi> A <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> here, to ſet them forth in their luſter, and in their brightneſſe, would well ſuite with ſuch a ſubject; but we muſt doe as we may.</p>
            <p>The Text is of <hi>Shew bread</hi> all along, and that belongs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly to the Prieſts. And in the Tabernacle where the golden Candleſtick was ſet, it was commanded, <hi>That the Table there ſhould be furniſhed with ſuch Bread;</hi> and ſo it is here. And that I may break to every one of you a morſell of it, and give to each of you his portion in due ſeaſon: Let us take a ſecond view of the Text in the particulars of it, branching themſelves out of theſe more generall Parts: And here out of the firſt part, The Perſon to whom the Epiſtle is directed, <hi>The Angel of the Church,</hi> we are to conſider.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What is meant by this Angel?</item>
               <item>2. Who in particular this Angel was?</item>
               <item>3. Whether under that Name he underſtand ſome one particular Perſon onely? or whether there were any more included under that name?</item>
               <item>4. Why he is repreſented under the name and notion of an Angel? <hi>To the Angel of the Church of</hi> Epheſus.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Then out of the next part of the Text, The Perſon from whom the Epiſtle is ſent, we are to conſider out of the firſt part of his deſcription, <hi>Holding the ſeven Starrs in his right hand;</hi> what? or who are meant by theſe ſeven Starrs? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it may not be literally underſtood of that famous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation clearly viſible in our Horizon, <hi>in dorſo Tauri,</hi> called by Aſtronomers, the <hi>Pleyades;</hi> by our vulgar people, in plain Engliſh, the ſeven ſtarrs? Or, if not them? then
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104483:4"/>who? or what elſe is meant by them. And thirdly, Why repreſented under the ſimilitude of <hi>the ſeven Starrs?</hi> And next, What is meant by his <hi>holding of them in his right hand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then out of the next part of his Deſcription, as he is repreſented, <hi>Walking between the ſeven golden Candleſticks,</hi> we are to enquire, VVhat theſe <hi>golden Candleſticks</hi> are? who they are that are repreſented by them? and why? And laſtly, what is meant by <hi>his walking in the midſt of them?</hi> not ſitting, nor ſtanding; but walking: <hi>Non in angulo, ſed in medio,</hi> in the midſt of them.</p>
            <p>Out of the third part, The ſpeciall notice that he takes of their works; We are to conſider, what works he means, and how, and why he is ſo exact in obſerving them, and taking notice of them? All theſe things clearly offer themſelves to our conſideration and enquiry. And if I ſhould metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically, and exactly treat of them all, I might well conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue my Diſcourſe as large as <hi>Paul</hi> did his Sermon, which he Preach't to this very Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. till Starr-light, and till we ſhould have occaſion to make uſe of theſe Candleſticks here before us, to finiſh it. But I am com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded brevity, and I will obſerve it, as well as I can, in ſo copious a ſubject as this is, in which, <hi>Crede mihi labor eſt, non levis eſſe brevis:</hi> But I have heard of foure ſorts of Preachers, The <hi>Quoter,</hi> the <hi>Noter,</hi> the <hi>Taunter,</hi> and the <hi>Flaunter:</hi> Amongſt all theſe, upon this account, I ſhall fall in with the ſecond ſort, I ſhall neither Taunt nor Flaunt, nor fill the Margin with Quotations; but onely note, as it were with an aſteriſme, and point with the ſinger at thoſe things which are moſt remarkable, <hi>&amp; tanquam Canis ad Nilum,</hi> hint and away. And firſt of the Perſon unto whom this Epiſtle is directed, here repreſented to us
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104483:5"/>under the Name and Notion of an Angel, <hi>To the Angel of the Church of</hi> Epheſus.</p>
            <p>Firſt, VVhat was this Angel? <hi>Pererius</hi> tells, and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally the current of Interpreters, that by <hi>the Angel</hi> here, is meant the Biſhop of the Church of <hi>Epheſus; Per Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum hunc, non alium intelligimus, quam Epiſcopum Eccleſiae Epheſinae;</hi> By <hi>the Angel</hi> here, we underſtand none other but the Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> And reaſon it ſelf ſuggeſts it, for it is clear by that which we Reade, <hi>Acts</hi> 20. and in the Epiſtle written by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> That there were many Paſtors and Teachers in that Metropoliticall Church; yet our Lord, writing unto the Church, doth not direct his Epiſtle indifferently to them all; but to one more eminent then all the reſt, one that was Superinten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent over all the reſt, whom here he ſtiles, <hi>The Angel of that Church;</hi> though there were many <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers</hi> in that great and populous City; yet they are not all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently ſtyled Angels, although they might all, in a way of reſemblance, be ſtyled Angels; yet not all, nor any of the reſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Angel:</hi> But to this Perſon he writes as to one more eminent then all the reſt, to one that had power, authority, and juriſdiction over the reſt, whom here he ſtyleth by an Emphaſis, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Angel, To the Angel of the Church of</hi> Epheſus.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> It appears then, there were diſtinctions, and different Orders and Degrees among the Clergy from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, even under the Goſpel. In our Saviours time, there was firſt himſelf, the Prince of the Order; then the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles; then the Evangeliſts; then the ſeventy Diſciples, all Miniſters of the Goſpel. But can you imagine that all theſe were of equall Dignity in the Church? In <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:104483:5"/>1.5. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> authorizes <hi>Titus, to Ordain Elders in every Church.</hi> That the Elders were <hi>Teaching Elders,</hi> it appears by their Ordination. But can any man imagine, that theſe Elders Ordeined by <hi>Titus,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> authorizing <hi>Titus</hi> to Ordain them, were all of an equall authority in the Church, <hi>Ejuſdem Ordinis, ejuſdem Dignitatis, ejuſdem Poteſtatis?</hi> Reaſon it ſelf ſpeaks the contrary; In Heaven above there is an Hierarchy: we Reade of <hi>Angels, and Arch-Angels, &amp;c.</hi> And why ſhould it ſeem ſo ſtrange that there is ſuch an one here below? and that we ſhould heare of Biſhops, and Arch-Biſhops, &amp;c. If it be uſefull in the Church Triumphant? ſurely in the Church Militant much more. So it was here in this Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> there were many Paſtors, many Prieſts, or Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters belonging to it, and Miniſtring in it; yet among all the reſt one more eminent then the reſt, of greater Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, Power, and Authority then the reſt, here ſtyled, The Angel of the Church: <hi>To the Angel òf the Church of</hi> Epheſus.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Quaery is, Who in particular this Angel was then Biſhop in that See: And 'tis generally noted to be <hi>Timothy:</hi> Sure we are, that <hi>Timothy</hi> was Biſhop there, and that much about this time; We have Scripture for that, in the Cloſe of the ſecond Epiſtle to <hi>Timothy,</hi> where <hi>Paul</hi> Dates, and Directs his Epiſtle thus, <hi>The ſecond Epiſtle to</hi> Timothy, <hi>Ordained the firſt Biſhop of the Church of the</hi> Epheſians, <hi>Written from</hi> Rome, <hi>when</hi> Paul <hi>was brought bèfore</hi> Nero <hi>the ſecond time.</hi> After whom, Saint <hi>John</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that writ this Epiſtle, Succeeded him in the ſame See, where he lived many years, and at laſt ended his dayes, a very old Man, and dyed in Peace in his Bed, and ſo did none of the Apoſtles, but he; all the reſt being Crowned
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:104483:6"/>with Martyrdome: For the latter of theſe, we have the Hiſtory of the Church: But for the former, we have the Canonicall Scripture it ſelf to confirm it: So that you cannot caſt Biſhops out of the Church Root and Branch, (as the cry goes among ſome of you) except you will burn your Bibles.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But why doth he write in the ſingular number, <hi>To the Angel of the Church,</hi> as to one? VVere there no more concerned in it? Surely yes, all the Clergy at the leaſt; ſo <hi>Rupertus, Dum ad Angelum ſcribit, ad totum Clerum ſcribit:</hi> VVhen he writes to <hi>the Angel,</hi> or <hi>Biſhop of the Church,</hi> he <hi>Writes to the whole body of the Clergy of that Church. Lyra</hi> goes further, <hi>In Angelo Eccleſiae, totam affatur Eccleſiam;</hi> In the Angel of the Church, he ſpeaks to the whole Church, however moſt eſpecially to the Paſtors and Miniſters of it. But why in the ſingular number, as to one? but becauſe he was their Chief, he was their Governour, he had the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of all the reſt, he had the Charge of them, as they had of the Flock of Chriſt, and of the Congregations un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him; he was to give them their Charge, to ſet them upon their Duty, and to ſee that they did diſcharge it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly; and therefore, as if they were all involved in him, and included in him, whatſoever is found good in them, is imputed unto him, and he is commended for it; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is found reproveable in them, is charged upon him all along throughout the whole Epiſtle, and he is blamed for it. Judge you then if he, and all his Succeſſors in the like Charge, have not reaſon to look into the Carriage and Behaviour of thoſe which are ſo immediately under their Government, and under their Charge; if they have not rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>to Overſee them, to Viſit them, to take an Account of them how they carry in their Places,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104483:6"/>and diſcharge their Duties in their ſeverall Charges.</hi> Surely it is but reaſonable, and neceſſary, that he ſhould take an Account of others, which is to give an Account for others unto God; and ſuch is the Caſe in the Text, <hi>To the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Church</hi> is the Epiſtle directed, of him is the Account required for all that are under his Charge and Government, eſpecially his Clergy, <hi>To the Angel of the Church of</hi> Epheſus, <hi>Write.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the main thing offered out of this ſuperſcription of the Epiſtle to be inquired into, is this; Why it is Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected <hi>to the Biſhop?</hi> (or who ever elſe are included in it) under the Name and Notion of <hi>an Angel, To the Angel of the Church.</hi> And Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> gives the Reaſon in a word; <hi>Propter ſimilitudinem,</hi> for the likeneſſe that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, and for the many properties wherein all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Paſtors, and Miniſters of the Church ſhould reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the Angels; and the reſemblances between them for which they are called by that Name, are principally theſe five.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Propter Dignitatem,</hi> For the Honour and Dignity that God hath put upon them; God hath Clothed them with Honour and Dignity above their Brethren, and <hi>hath Anointed them with the Oyle of Grace and gladneſſe above their fellows;</hi> Hath Dignified them with the higheſt Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles that Men can be capable of, <hi>Spirituall Fathers, Paſtors, Rulers, Embaſſadors, Starrs, Angels,</hi> that they may be Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable in the Eyes of the People; it is much for his own Honour that it ſhould be ſo; it is for the Honour of his Service that it ſhould be ſo; it is much for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of their Miniſtery that it ſhould be ſo; it is for the Honour of the People that it ſhould be ſo; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath he Commanded, that we ſhould <hi>account them wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104483:7"/>of double Honour,</hi> if not for their own ſake, yet for their works ſake, and for their Maſters ſake, we ſhould not think much to Honour them whom God doth Honour: And let them whom God hath thus Honoured, take heed they doe not diſhonour him, nor themſelves. Remember the <hi>Item</hi> given to <hi>Elyes</hi> Sonns in this very caſe; <hi>Thoſe which Honour me, I will Honour; but thoſe that deſpiſe me, ſhall be deſpiſed,</hi> 1 Sam. 2.30. made good <hi>Malach.</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Propter Miniſtrationem;</hi> Paſtors, and Miniſters of the Church, are called Angels, for the likeneſſe of their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration with that of the Angels: <hi>Angels are Miniſtring Spirits, ſent out for the good of thoſe that ſhall be the Heires of ſalvation,</hi> Heb. 1.14. Paſtors and Miniſters are ſuch for all the world, called, commiſſionated, and ſent out for the good of thoſe that ſhall be the Heires of Salvation, to Preach unto them the Goſpel of Grace; To Publiſh and Declare unto them the Miſtery of Godlineſſe; To Proclaime the glad tydings of Salvation; To Inſtruct them in the way of Life; To Comfort, to Confirme them, to ſtrengthen them, and every way to Build them up upon their moſt holy Faith, and ſo to fit and prepare them for the Glory that is intended them: their very Name imports their Duty, <hi>Angels, Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers from God to Man;</hi> And the Meſſage that they bring is good, 'tis <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>good newes, tydings of Peace, and of good things: How beautifull therefore ought their very Feet to be upon the Mountains, which are ſhod with the preparation of ſuch Goſpel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Angels, <hi>Propter Scientiam, &amp; Sapientiam,</hi> for their wiſedom and knowledge; Angels are wiſe, and knowing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits; <hi>As an Angel of God, ſo is my Lord the King to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern good and evill,</hi> ſayes the widdow of <hi>Tekoah</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> 2. Sam. 14.17. And <hi>verſe</hi> the 20. <hi>My Lord the King is
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104483:7"/>Wiſe, as an Angel of God, to know all things:</hi> Angels are wiſe, and knowing Spirits; ſuch ought Paſtors and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Churches to be, <hi>Wiſe, and Knowing: The Prieſts Lips muſt preſerve Knowledge, and the people ſhall ſeek the Law at his Mouth: for he is the Meſſenger of the Lord of Hoſts,</hi> Malac. 2.7. The <hi>Roman</hi> Orator was wont to ſay of the Lawyers Houſe, that it was <hi>Oraculum Civitatis,</hi> the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of the City: I am ſure it ought to be ſo of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines: The Divines Reſidentiary Houſe ought to be, <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum Civitatis,</hi> from whence any of the People ought to fetch Inſtruction, Direction, Reſolution, Satisfaction in all their Doubts, and Difficulties; <hi>Tanquam ab Oraculo,</hi> as from an Oracle; and this requires much knowledge, wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and prudence: <hi>He muſt not be a Novice,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Tim. 3.6. <hi>He muſt be as a Steward,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>plentifully furniſhed, that may bring out of his Treaſury things New and Old.</hi> God will not ſend a Meſſage by the Leggs of the Lame; nor make Blind men Seers, nor Dumbe men his Orators: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi deſinit Philoſophus, ibi incipit Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us.</hi> It was wont to be ſaid, <hi>Where the Philoſopher ends, there the Phyſitian begins:</hi> I am ſure it ought to be ſo with the Divines: Arts and Sciences, Knowledge in the Learned Languages, Hiſtories, and all other kinds of Humane Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, were wont to be accounted the Stayres into the Pulpit, the Handmaids to Divinity: But how ordinary hath it been in theſe latter and looſer Times for young Neophytes to skip over all theſe at one jumpe into the Pulpit, and there with great Confidence and Impudence, the onely Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of Ignorance, to vent their own raw Fancies, or ſuch things which they have taken up upon Truſt, from ſuch Authors as they have light upon, or what they have taken from the Mouth of their admired Teachers, by <hi>Brachygra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phie,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104483:8"/>and ſo Communicate them unto the people, apt to take any new Impreſſions, and fill them with varietie of Fancies and Innovations.</p>
            <p>The fourth property wherein the Biſhops, Paſtors, and Miniſters of Churches doe reſemble the Angels, and for which they are ſo called, is, <hi>Propter Celeritatem,</hi> for their readineſſe, chearfulneſſe, and ſwiftneſſe in Executing the Commands of Almighty God. Angels are repreſented to us Winged, and thoſe Wings not let down, and clapt to their ſides; but raiſed up, <hi>expanſit</hi> and ſtretched out, to ſhew their readineſſe to execute the will of the Heavenly Father; they ſtand in his preſence, their Eye is upon him, they doe but watch for the word of Command, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they are upon the Wing: They doe not goe, but runne; not runne, but fly, ſuch ſhould be our readineſſe in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the will of our God: we muſt not runne before we be ſent; but being ſent, we muſt not linger, delay, nor make excuſes, we muſt not Drive heavily in his Service, the wheeles of our obedience, muſt be oyled with Chearful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Alacrity, that we may move ſwiftly in all our Duties and Performances; as we dayly Pray, ſo we muſt dayly Practiſe <hi>That his will may be done on Earth, as it is in Heaven;</hi> and we ſee how the Angels doe his will, with winged Chearfulneſſe and Swiftneſſe; Goe thou and doe likewiſe.</p>
            <p>The fifth reſemblance for which Biſhops, Paſtors, and Miniſters of the Church are ſtyled Angels, is, <hi>Propter Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem,</hi> for their Holineſſe and Purity: Angels are pure Creatures, ſo had they need be that ſtand in the preſence of the holy God, and are admitted ſo neer unto him, in this reſpect we muſt be as the Angels, and that upon the ſame account. <hi>Moſes</hi> tells <hi>Korah,</hi> Numb. 16.9. <hi>That the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104483:8"/>Lord had taken him neer unto him, to doe the ſervice of the Tabernacle:</hi> Even ſo we that are the Lords Prieſts ſet a part to doe the ſervice of the Tabernacle, and to Miniſter before him in holy things, are taken neer unto the Lord: And he hath ſaid, <hi>He will be ſanctified in them that come neer him,</hi> Levit. 10. Oh what a hatefull thing it is to God and Man, to ſee a profane perſon, polluted and beſmeared with all manner of impiety, impurity, and uncleanneſſe, to draw neer to God in holy Services, with his polluted Heart, polluted Lips, polluted Life, and polluted Hands, to pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute all that he toucheth? it is a wonder that in ſuch ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the holy God doth not break out upon them, to ſtrike them through with a Thunderbolt, or by Fire from Heaven avenge himſelf upon their preſumption, as he did upon <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> in the like Caſe, and for the ſame Sinn, <hi>Levit.</hi> 10. And how hatefull it is to Man, we may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive by that which <hi>Ely</hi> his Sonns are Charged with, in the ſame Caſe, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.17. <hi>You make the Lords People to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the Sacrifice of the Lord.</hi> Woe be to us, if through our profanneſſe, or irreverent handling of holy things, we make the Lords People to abhorre the Sacrifice of the Lord; take heed we handle holy things in a holy manner, that we put off our Shooes when we approach the burning Buſh, and ſtand upon holy Ground, that we waſh our Hands in innocency, before we compaſſe the Altar: All the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and purifyings under the Law, did but Typically Teach us, how holy we ought to be: Our very Garments that we wears, reade unto us Lectures of holineſſe and purity. In the Conſecration of <hi>Aaron</hi> to the Office of the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, among other Religious Ceremonies, it was Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>That the Blood of the Sacrifice ſhould be Sprinkled upon his right Eare, and upon the Thumbe of his right Hand, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104483:9"/>upon the great Toe of his right Foot;</hi> And what did all this ſignifie? but that the Lords Prieſts muſt be Sanctified throughout, and from Top to Toe Conſecrated as holy un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord. The Motto of the High-Prieſts Miter, was, <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord;</hi> It ſhould be the Motto of every one of our Hearts, our Lips, our Lives, and all our Service ſhould Proclaime, <hi>Holineſſe to the Lord.</hi> We are here ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Angels,</hi> to ſhew, That we ſhould walk before the Lord even in Angelicall purity and holineſſe.</p>
            <p>We ſhould now come to ſpeak of the Perſon from whom this Epiſtle is ſent: But by the way, we may not omit the Charge here given to Saint <hi>John,</hi> concerning the things to be ſignified unto the Church from him; and that is, To Write them down: <hi>To the Angel of the Church of</hi> Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>Write.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Saint <hi>John</hi> had been an Authentique Meſſenger to have delivered <hi>Viva voce,</hi> byword of Mouth, a Meſſage from Chriſt to the Church: But Chriſt doth not think that ſufficient, but he muſt Write: The Reaſon was, Thoſe things that he there wrote to that Church, did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern all other Chriſtian Churches to the worlds end, <hi>He that hath an Eare muſt hearken unto them.</hi> And therefore that they may come to the knowledge of them, it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary they ſhould be written. Secondly. Things delivered by word of Mouth, and ſo tranſmitted from Mouth to Mouth by Tradition, are ſubject to be corrupted, miſreported, to admit of Addition, Diminution, Alteration, there can be no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in them, but <hi>Litera Scripta manet.</hi> Away then with all your Popiſh Traditions, Anabaptiſticall Revelations, Fallacious <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nwritten Verities,</hi> as they call them, when you ſpeak of the Canon, whereby we ſhould be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:104483:9"/>in matters of Faith and Manners in order to our Eternall ſalvation. God hath better provided for his Church then ſo, <hi>By giving us a more ſure Word of the Prophets and Apoſtles, and our Lord himſelf, all in Writing, unto which we ſhall doe well to take heed, as to the Lights ſhining in a dark place, to guide our Feet in the wayes of truth, life, and peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We now come to conſider of the Perſon, from whom the Epiſtle is ſent. <hi>Intererit multum</hi> Davuſne <hi>loquatur, beruſne:</hi> It adds much to the luſter and authority of that which is written, to conſider from whom it is written; And that is here, from this wonderfull Perſon deſcribed in the Text, by <hi>Holding the ſeven Starrs in his right hand, and walking in the midſt of the ſeven Golden Candleſticks.</hi> As the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſay</hi> once askt the queſtion, <hi>Iſay</hi> 63.1. <hi>Who is this that commeth from Edom, with Garments died red from Bozrah?</hi> So here, <hi>Who is this wonderfull Perſon, which here we ſee walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the midſt of the ſeven Golden Candleſticks? Why; It is none other but the Sonne of God, the Lord of the Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, and the owner of them, the very ſame which we ſaw be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, bolding the ſeven Starrs in his right hand.</hi> But hath he no Name? <hi>Yes:</hi> But the Spirit thought it more fit to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him here in a Glorious Viſion, to ſet him forth in ſuch a Heavenly Deſcription and Periphraſis, as might ſtrike in the Church an awfull reverence of ſo Divine a Majeſty, to <hi>tremble at his Word, and carefully to heed it;</hi> in the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, the Threatnings, the Inſtructions, the Admonitions, the Reprehenſions, and all the ſeverall diſpenſations of it, as the <hi>Word of the Mighty God, and not of Man, the King. Chiefe Prieſt, and Prophet of the Church, and one that was perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the midſt of them, and had a continuall Eye upon them, and would take a ſtrict account of them;</hi> therefore is he ſet forth not by his Name, but by a deſcription.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:104483:10"/>
            <p> In this Deſcription here, are two parts, we muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of them both in their Order: The former of them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents him to us, <hi>Holding the ſeven Starrs in his right hand.</hi> Firſt then, <hi>What is meant by theſe ſeven Starrs?</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>What is meant by his holding of them in his right hand?</hi> As to the firſt, It is no injury to truth to underſtand them in a Literall ſence of that famous Conſtellation in Heaven, which in a clear Night is viſible in our Horizon, <hi>in dorſo Tauri,</hi> which our Vulgar People call, <hi>the ſeven Starrs;</hi> Aſtronomers, <hi>the Pleyades,</hi> and by a Synechdoche, for the whole number of the Starts in the Firmament; all which, <hi>this wonderfull Perſon holdeth in his right hand: He telleth the number of the Starrs, and calleth them all by their Names; He Created them at the firſt; He aſsigned to them their Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Firmament, their Conſtellations, their Motions, their Vertues, their Influences which he can cauſe them to ſend forth when he pleaſeth, and when he pleaſeth reſtrain them: Canſt thou ſtay the ſweet Influences of the Pleyades? or binde the Hands of Orion?</hi> thou canſts not; <hi>But he that made them, and gave them their Influences, can.</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>Aſtra regunt Homines, ſed regit aſtra Deus:</hi>
               </q> The Starrs have a ſtrong Influence upon Men, and upon the ſubſtellary Bodies: but he that made them hath a ſtronger Influence upon them; <hi>He holdeth them in his right hand, guides them, moves them, orders them as it pleaſeth him;</hi> and therfore <hi>feare not the ſignes of Heaven,</hi> Jer. 10.2. but feare the God of Heaven; Look not ſo much at the Starrs, as at the Hand, and at him <hi>that holdeth them in his right hand.</hi> Thus if we underſtand theſe Starrs in a Literall ſence, the words will beare it well enough; the Expoſition is true, but not ſo genuine; 'tis ſure enough our Lord did allude unto thoſe Starrs we ſpeak of in this Expreſſion? But in the genuine
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104483:10"/>Interpretation of them, he leads us another way, to a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphoricall ſence, <hi>Revel.</hi> 1. <hi>and the laſt,</hi> and by theſe <hi>ſeven Starrs,</hi> underſtands, <hi>the ſeven Angels of theſe ſeven Churches;</hi> and by thoſe Angels, <hi>the Biſhops, and Chiefe Paſtors of thoſe Churches; and under them, all the other Miniſters, Paſtors, and Teachers, which here he ſtyleth, ſo many Starrs:</hi> But what is it that the <hi>Spirit would ſay unto the Churches,</hi> by this Metaphoricall Expreſſion? Surely this is that which he would ſay,</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>That all Biſhops, Paſtors, and Miniſters of the Church ſhould be as Starrs in the ſeverall Churches, and Charges where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are fixt, and that in a ſix-fold reſemblance, for which they are there ſo ſtyled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Propter Lucem,</hi> for the Light that ought to be in them, and by which they ought to ſhine unto others: It is the property of the Starrs to ſhine, and to give light to the dark places of the Earth, and that in the Night time when there is moſt need of it; Remember we are Starrs, and Starrs muſt ſhine: <hi>We are the Light of the World, and muſt not be put under a Buſhell, but ſet up on a Candleſtick, that we may give Light to all that are about us.</hi> It is a high Teſtimony that our Saviour gave <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, <hi>That he was a ſhin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Light.</hi> Tis ſaid of the Fathers, met in the Councell of <hi>Nice,</hi> that they were, <hi>Totius Orbis Lumina:</hi> It was ſaid of Saint <hi>Baſil, That he was in his Pulpit as Thunder; and in his exemplary Converſation, as Lightning.</hi> We muſt ſhine by our Doctrine, and ſhine by our Works, and ſhine by our Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Converſation; by all theſe we muſt <hi>ſo ſhine before Men, that they may ſee our good works,</hi> as well as hear our good words, that ſo they may be moved, <hi>to glorifie our Father which is in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:104483:11"/> 2. But Light without Heat, is but a kind of <hi>Ignis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus;</hi> there muſt be Heate within, as well as Light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, heate of Love, and heate of Zeale; <hi>John was a ſhining and a burning Light;</hi> he ſhin'd in his Doctrine, and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary life without, and he burn'd within with Love and Zeal. Remember we are Sacrificers, and thoſe Sacrifices were ever moſt acceptable which were offered by fire unto the Lord; without this holy fire to quicken, and to warm us, we ſhall be but cold in our performances, perfunctory in our ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, we ſhall Drive heavily in the wayes of God, and doe the work of the Lord but negligently: Zeale is the wings of the ſoule that lifts it up, and carries it on ſwiftly in holy performances, the oyle of the wheeles of out obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that makes them run chearfully; it will put us upon all our Duties with earneſtneſſe, fervency, devotion, affection, and that which we doe for God, or to God, it will make us to doe it heartily and throughly; of all others we had need to be <hi>fervent in ſpirit, ſerving the Lord,</hi> from whoſe Zeal, all our People are to take Fire.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Starrs, <hi>Propter Influentiam;</hi> Biſhops, Paſtors, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Church are called <hi>Starrs,</hi> by reaſon of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence that they have upon the people, and the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions depending upon them: <hi>Radius eſt vehiculum lucis, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loris &amp; influentiae;</hi> The Starrs and other Luminaries of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, doe by the Rayes and Beams which they ſend forth, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey not onely Light and Heate, but ſtrong influence alſo into the inferiour Bodies. <hi>Canſt thou ſtay the ſweet influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Pleyades,</hi> ſaith <hi>Job,</hi> ſpeaking of thoſe very ſeven Starrs unto which the Text doth allude: Even ſo the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Miniſters of the Church, the Church-Starrs doe convey unto the people under them, ſtrong influence, good or bad; if they be benigne Starrs, then the influence Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104483:11"/>from them is good, ſaving, healing, comforting, revive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing influence: But if they be malignant Starrs, the influence Flowing from them muſt needs be like unto themſelves, blaſting and diſaſterous. There are ſome Aſtronomers tell us, <hi>That unto every Creature here below in this inferiour world, there is aſsigned a</hi> Starr, <hi>from whoſe influence it doth receive Vigor, Life, and Vegetation:</hi> Not much unlike the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Papiſts, <hi>That aſsigne to every Man borne into the World, an Angel to be his Guardian:</hi> And of the <hi>Manichees, Which aſsigne to every ſoule a good Angel and a bad; the one drawing him to that which is good, the other to that which is evill.</hi> I leave them to defend their own Opinions; this is ſure, That from every of us Church-Starrs, there Darts out a Beame, or a Ray, which derives influence from us, good or bad, to every ſoule that lives under our aſpect; if we prove malignant Starrs, and that influence from us be Killing, and Deſtructive, woe unto us; How many ſoules ſhall we have to anſwer for in that caſe, periſhing through us? Remember we are Starrs, ſee the <hi>influence</hi> which we ſend forth to thoſe that depend upon us be good <hi>influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Propter Ordinem.</hi> Biſhops, Paſtors, and Miniſters of the Churches, are ſtyled Starrs, for the <hi>Order that is among them,</hi> and which they ought with all due care, to keep and obſerve. <hi>The</hi> Starrs <hi>in their Order fought againſt</hi> Siſera, <hi>Judg.</hi> 5. We have <hi>Siſera's</hi> to fight againſt, and if ever we will fight proſperouſly, we muſt fight in Order. In all Order there is ſubordination, as well as Ordination; and there are Degrees, <hi>Secundum ſub, &amp; ſupra.</hi> There are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Magnitudes, <hi>and one Starr differeth from another in Glory.</hi> The moſt Reverend Fathers in God, the Lords Arch-Biſhops, and Biſhops, they are Starrs of the firſt Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104483:12"/>The Reverend Prelates and Dignitaries in Cathedrall Churches, they are Starrs of a ſecond Magnitude. VVe Country Prieſts, we are Starrs too, but of a leſſer ſize, that move in a lower Sphere; <hi>Minores Nobiles Coeli in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferioris,</hi> the Minors of the Inferiour world; we muſt all be content with our Stations, and with our Standings, and every one move in that ſphere in which Providence hath plac't and fixt him. Thoſe that are of the greater Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, muſt not deſpiſe thoſe that are leſſer; thoſe that are of leſſer, muſt not envie thoſe that are greater, but eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one muſt move in his own ſphere, every one Act in his own Place, and in that Conſtellation wherein he is fixt; there he muſt ſhine, and there he muſt ſend forth Light, and Heate, and Influence, and doe all the good he can: If the Starrs of Heaven ſhould change their Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Croſſe their Motions, and juſtle one with another? what muſt needs follow, but a <hi>Conflagration</hi> in Heaven? And if the Church-Starrs here below, ſhall doe the like, they muſt needs threaten Combuſtion on Earth. If <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons</hi> Bells once begin to jangle, become out of Tune, and Ring Croſſe? what doe they cry, but Fire in the Church, which will ſoon take hold of the Kingdom too, and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine all together? But remember we are Starrs, and we muſt keep our Courſe, move in our own ſphere, and keep in Order; that's the fourth Reſemblance, for which we are called Starrs.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The fifth is, In reſpect of our Fixedneſſe and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement in our Charges; The Starrs in the Firmament are Fixed Starrs; thoſe ſeven more particularly (unto which this Scripture ſeems to allude) in a famous Conſtellation: ſuch ſhould the Church-Starrs be, Fixed Starrs; <hi>Non ſtellae erraticae, non cadentes;</hi> Not wandring Starrs, not fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104483:12"/>Starrs, not Meteors, ſuddainly appearing, and as ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly diſappearing: But fixed Starrs, ſetled in that place of the Heaven, of the Church here below, which Providence hath aſſigned unto them; and there being diſpoſed of, they muſt fix, there they muſt reſide, there they muſt ſhine, thence they muſt ſend forth their <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences,</hi> to the enlivening, comforting, and refreſhing of all thoſe that are under their <hi>influences,</hi> and their <hi>aſpect,</hi> ſuteable to their ſeverall Poſitures, Capaſities, Priviledges, and Honours.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſixth Reſemblance between the Starrs, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Miniſters of the Churches, is in their borowed Light; the iniate Light of the Starrs is but weak; the beſt Light by which they ſhine, is but mutuatitious, derived from the Sunne, the Fountain of Light: Even ſo it is with our Church-Starrs, the Light that is in us, is not our own, it is a borrowed Light <hi>that comes down from the Father of Lights, and is derived from the Sonne of Righteouſneſſe, ariſing over us, with healing under his Wings, the Fountain of Light, out of whoſe fulneſſe we all receive Grace for Grace.</hi> And this Conſideration ſhould teach us two things. Firſt, <hi>Humility:</hi> Here's no ground for boaſting: Saint <hi>Paul</hi> pricks the Bladder of that ſwelling pride, and makes it fall, when he puts us in mind of our Poverty and Dependency, <hi>What haſt thou, which thou haſt not received?</hi> And if Men will be boaſting, let them boaſt of that which is their own; <hi>The Light that we have, is not our own,</hi> be the gifts and parts in thee never ſo great, the Light that is in thee never ſo clear, ſo illuſtrious; yet ſay of it all, as the Sonne of the Prophet did of the Axe which he let fall into the water, <hi>Alas Maſter, it was but borrowed;</hi> the glory of them is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104483:13"/>due to the Lender, not to the Borrower; to the Giver, not to the Receiver; <hi>But of him, and from him, and by him are all theſe; therefore to him be the glory of them all, for ever and ever, of him the Father, from him the Sonne, and by him the holy Ghoſt</hi> are they all; <hi>And therefore to him the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Trinity, be the glory of them all for evermore.</hi> Secondly, This ſhould teach us Charity, in the communicating of this Light to others, which is committed unto us for that very end; And therefore we are Charged with this Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, not onely upon the account of Charity, but of Juſtice, and Faithfulneſſe in our truſt: <hi>As every one hath recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſo let him diſtribute, as Stewards of the manifold gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of God:</hi> Stewards are to give Accounts, as well as to take them; and the greater their Receipts are, the greater Accounts doe they make them lyable unto. A Day will come, when it ſhall be ſaid unto them, <hi>Redde rationem Villicationis tuae; Give an Account of thy Stewardſhip:</hi> And ſuch are we all in this Caſe. The Gifts that we have are not our own: they are committed to us but in truſt; we Receive them to Have, but not to Hold; we muſt Communicate. The Starrs doe not ſhine to themſelves; but to the inferiour world, to give Light to others, and that in the darkeſt times too of the Night, when there is moſt need of them. Such Starrs muſt we be, <hi>To ſhine into the World: To give Light to them that fit in Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in the ſhadow of Death, to guide our Feet into the wayes of Truth and Peace.</hi> And thus you ſee what it is <hi>which the ſpirit would ſay unto the Churches,</hi> in this <hi>ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile,</hi> in reſembling the <hi>Paſtors and Miniſters of it by the Starres.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:104483:13"/>
            <p> But what is meant, by <hi>Holding them in his right hand?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are five things intimated to us in this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>great Care that Almighty God hath of them,</hi> to ſecure them, to preſerve them, to protect them, <hi>that the Sonnes of violence ſhall not come neer to touch them, or to hurt them; He that toucheth you, toucheth the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of mine Eye,</hi> Who dare come ſo neer to hurt thoſe which Chriſt <hi>holdeth in his right hand,</hi> but his left hand will be ready to avenge them?</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>The great Honour that he is pleaſed to doe them,</hi> to take them ſo neer unto himſelf, as into his <hi>right hand.</hi> The Right hand is a place of Honour and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. <hi>Chriſt ſitteth on the right Hand of the Father. The Sheep are placed on the right Hand of Chriſt.</hi> When <hi>Solomon</hi> would Honour his Mother, he cauſed a Throne to be ſet, <hi>and her to be placed at his right Hand.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, and Miniſters of Churches, they are on Gods right Hand, they are in his right Hand, they are there as Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets of his right Hand, as pretious Stones in his Signer, Illuſtrious and Glorious. Great is the Honour that he is pleaſed to put upon them, even here in the Church; How ſtudious ought we to be of his Honour, that hath thus honoured us, and of our own too, that we carry as becomes us in that high Relation, Calling, Dignity, Name, and Place that we beare in Gods <hi>right Hand, that ſo we way ſit on his right Hand hereafter, in whoſe preſence is fulneſſe of joy, and at whoſe right hand are pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The advantage that we have of being abundantly il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luminated by the light of his countenance, at ſo neer a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance;</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:104483:14"/>The neerer the Starrs are to the Fountain of Light, the ſtronger muſt needs be the irradiation from it, and their illumination by it: Behold, we are neer unto the Lord, <hi>Starrs in his right Hand;</hi> how ſtrong then muſt needs be the irradiation from ſo Glorious a Preſence, through the beams of his countenance darting upon us. In was ſaid of <hi>Moſes,</hi> that when he came out of the Mount, <hi>his Face did ſhine, that the people could not look upon him for the glory of it.</hi> Behold, we are in the Mount with God, we are taken neer unto him; the Light in us ſhould be ſo great, our Gifts and Graces ſo illuſtrious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſplendent, that our people ſhould look upon us with dazled Eyes, in admiration of our ſpirituall excellencies; while we behold with open face the Glory of the Lord, it ſhould be our care and indeavour, and will be our hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe too, to be transformed into the ſame Image from Glory to Glory, and that that God, <hi>which made the light to ſhine out of darkneſſe,</hi> may ſhine into our Hearts, to give the light of the Glory of God, in the Face of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By this expreſſion is intimated, <hi>the continuall Eye that God hath upon us, to obſerve our carriage, and our behaviour in our Callings, and in our reſpective Churches and Charges.</hi> We cannot be in <hi>his right Hand,</hi> but we muſt be under <hi>his right Eye too,</hi> and that is as a Flame of fire, not ſo much for the anger, as for the perſpicacity of it. Of all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and Callings amongſt men, there are none that he doth more ſtrictly obſerve, or take a more exact account of, then he doth of us. How punctually and particularly doth he Charge the <hi>Angels of theſe ſeven Churches,</hi> in the ſecond and third Chapters of this Book; <hi>This thou baſt, for which I commend thee: And theſe and theſe things I
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104483:14"/>have againſt thee;</hi> imagine it every one of us, as ſpoken unto our ſelves. A Day will come, when he will deale as punctually with us, as he doth here with them; In the meane time, <hi>He knows our Works, and fees our Wayes, and our Walkings; his Flaming and Fiery Eye is upon us: Oh what manner of Men ought we to be in all holy converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and godlineſſe?</hi> How circumſpectly ought we to walk? How exactly to order all our goings and doings, that are under the inſpection of ſo perſpicatious, ſo ſevere an Eye?</p>
            <p n="5">5. By this Expreſſion is intimated to us, <hi>The Power that Almighty God hath in his Hand, and the liberty that he reſerveth unto himſelf, to diſpoſe of theſe Starre as he pleaſeth, to hold forth this Hand, with the Starrs in it, to what part of the world he pleaſeth, and there to continue it as long as he pleaſeth, and when he pleaſeth to turn his Hand another way, even which may he pleaſeth, with the Starrs in it, to give light to them that ſit in darkneſſe, and in the ſhadow of death; and to leave the other from whom he took it in the darkneſſ, in which at the firſt, he found them.</hi> Beloved, theſe Starrs doe not ſhine to any place of the world, of the Church, by chance: No, not in particular Churches, there is a Providence in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of them. In the 16th. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> we have a clear evidence of it; there were three bright Starrs, faine would they have ſhined in <hi>Aſia,</hi> but they received a prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from the holy Ghoſt, <hi>The holy Ghoſt forbad them,</hi> ver. 6. Then <hi>they aſſayed to ſhine into</hi> Bithynia: <hi>but the ſpirit ſuffered them not,</hi> ver. 7. The Ruler, and Diſpoſer of the Starrs, had otherwiſe determined, that they ſhould <hi>goe to Macedonia, and ſhine there; and there did this Hand hold them forth for a ſeaſon,</hi> ver. 12. The Starrs muſt ſhine where
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104483:15"/>he will have them, and as long as he will have them, and no longer: Theſe <hi>ſeven Churches of Aſia,</hi> are an evidence of this truth at this day. Over them did Chriſt <hi>hold forth this Hand, with the Starrs in it at this time, and a long while after,</hi> untill he was weary of holding it forth: and by reaſon of their barrenneſſe, and unthankfulneſſe, their irreligion, and Apoſtaſie, they gave him juſt Cauſe to Complain, <hi>That all the day long, he had ſtretched out his Arme to an unthankfull, and a gain-ſaying people; and then to what purpoſe ſhould he hold it forth there any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger?</hi> In his wiſedom and juſtice he turned <hi>his Hand</hi> from them, and held it forth more <hi>Weſtward, to the Weſterne Churches:</hi> And ſince that, more <hi>Northward,</hi> to theſe Parts of the world, the Inhabitants of the Iſland, the Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of <hi>Japhet,</hi> amongſt whom we are: And now, by the bleſſing of God, we have enjoy'd the Light under them many years: But take heed, leaſt for the ſame ſinns, for which God turn'd <hi>his Hand</hi> from <hi>Shem</hi> to <hi>Japhet;</hi> he again remove <hi>his Hand</hi> from <hi>Japhet</hi> to <hi>Cham:</hi> and when he doth ſo, leaſt as upon that remove, he left <hi>Shem</hi> in darkneſſe; ſo upon this turne, he alſo leave us in that darkneſſe, wherein he found us. Beloved, there is an Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Propheſie, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.27. <hi>God ſhall perſwade</hi> Japhet, <hi>and he ſhall dwell in the Tents of</hi> Shem, <hi>and</hi> Canaan <hi>ſhall be his ſervant.</hi> What is meant by <hi>Shem</hi> there? but the Church, which was firſt Planted in thoſe <hi>Eaſterne</hi> Parts, which were the Habitation of <hi>Shem.</hi> What is meant by <hi>Japhet</hi>'s <hi>dwelling in his Tents?</hi> but his ſucceeding of <hi>Shem</hi> in the Priviledges of the Church, by tranſlating the Goſpel out of theſe <hi>Eaſterne</hi> Parts of the world, into theſe more <hi>Weſterly</hi> and <hi>Northerly</hi> Quarters of the world, which were the Lot of <hi>Japhets</hi> Inheritance, and in which his Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104483:15"/>ſeated themſelves, and amongſt whom we are, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from him by <hi>Gomer.</hi> By vertue of this Promiſe are we this Day <hi>the Church, and dwell in the Tents of</hi> Shem. But what doe we think of <hi>Canaan</hi> all this while? All this while he hath been a ſervant. <hi>But is there not a time when he ſhall ſhake off the Yoke of ſervitude? ſhall all thoſe Parts of</hi> America <hi>be for ever forgotten? ſhall Light never appear in them?</hi> Me thinks I ſee <hi>the Day-ſpring from on high, begin to viſit them:</hi> Me thinks I ſee the Beames of the Morning Sunne, begin to breake out upon them, in the promulgation of the Goſpel in <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginia,</hi> one of the outward skirts of that mighty Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent: And I am confident it will (as the Sunne) ſhine forth more and more, unto the perfect Day. I doe not doubt but God hath a great people among them to be gathered, and that there will be a glorious Church a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, before the Conſummation of the world: But take heed, leaſt as I intimated before, as God turning <hi>his Hand</hi> from <hi>Shem</hi> to <hi>Japhet,</hi> left <hi>Shem</hi> in darkneſſe, under which to this Day he lyes: So when God ſhall turne <hi>his Hand, with the Starrs</hi> in it from <hi>Japhet</hi> to <hi>Cham,</hi> or <hi>Canaan,</hi> he leave us alſo in the Darkeneſſe wherein at the firſt he found us, and their Sunne-riſing, be our Sunne-ſetting, our Barrenneſſe, Unfruitfulneſſe, Apoſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, falling from our firſt Love, our Schiſmes and Diviſions, our Hypocriſie, Formality, generall irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe and profaneneſſe, ſeem to portend and beſpeak no leſſe; preſages of it we have ſure, our Golden Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks lately tottering, and ſore ſhaken, the Famous Lights in them put out, others burning in them blue, and dimly; all manner of Hereſies that ever the <hi>Church</hi> hath been peſtered withall Revived, Countenanced, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged;
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104483:16"/>the Seameleſſe Coate of Chriſt Torne and Rent into an hundred pieces, by Sects, Schiſmes, and Diviſions, Factions, and Fractions; The Diſcipline of the Church layd by, the holy Worſhip deſpiſed, and trampled under foor, the Sacraments throwne out, all Ordinances, but Preaching, and Extemporary Praying cryed downe; the loweſt of the people made Prieſts, and the Prieſts made the loweſt of the people; the Churches turn'd into Stables, and Stables into Churches; And how much did all this come ſhort of the <hi>Abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of deſolation, ſtanding in the holy place?</hi> How neer did all this come to the execution of the judgement threatned againſt <hi>Epheſus</hi> in this Chapter, <hi>Of removing the Candleſticks out of their places?</hi> Well, bleſſed be God, they are not yet removed, they yet ſtand in their places, the Lights ſhining and burning in them, <hi>the right Hand of the Almighty is yet ſtretch't forth over us, with the Starrs ſhining in it.</hi> Let us be admoniſhed by all theſe threatning puniſhments, to walk in the light of them better then ever we have done, while we have it amongſt us, <hi>as Children of the Light, to walk up to the Light, to rejoyce in it, to be thankfull for it, and to bring forth the fruit of it:</hi> this is the beſt way to keep it, and to continue it among us. And thus you heare, <hi>what it is which the Spirit ſaith unto the Churches, in this Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphoricall Expreſsion, Of holding the Starrs in his right Hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It followeth now, That we conſider of the next Part of the Deſcription, <hi>Of this Wonderfull Perſon Chriſt the Sonne of God, as he is here repreſented, Walking in the midſt of the ſeven Golden Candleſticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:104483:16"/>
            <p> Not to trouble you with the ſpeculations of Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitors upon this ſacred and miſterious number of ſeven, ſo often mentioned in this Myſticall Book, in all the Viſions which Saint <hi>John</hi> ſaw, <hi>Seven Spirits, ſeven Angels, ſeven Starrs, ſeven Candleſticks, ſeven Seales, ſeven Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, ſeven Heads, ſeven Hills, ſeven Vialls, ſeven Plagues,</hi> all by <hi>ſevens,</hi> a ſacred and miſterious Number; and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are the Myſteries which ſome perſpicatious witts have told us of, conteyned in that Number. But to paſſe by that. Two things we have here to enquire into:
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>What is meant by theſe Candleſticks?</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>What by his Walking in the midſt of them?</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And for the firſt, our Lord himſelf hath Interpreted it unto our Hands, what is meant by them. In the laſt verſe of the Precedent Chapter, <hi>The ſeven Golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks, are the ſeven Churches,</hi> meaning of <hi>Aſia.</hi> Where take up this Obſervation by the way.</p>
            <p>That notwithſtanding there were many Corruptions in them, in Doctrine, in Worſhip, in Diſcipline, in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in matters both of Faith and Manners; yet our Saviour ſtill vouchſafeth them the Name of <hi>Churches: The ſeven Candleſticks, are the ſeven Churches.</hi> Epheſus <hi>is fallen from her firſt love,</hi> ver. 4. <hi>Smyrna</hi> had Hipocrites among them, <hi>Which ſaid, they were Jews, and were not,</hi> ver. 9. <hi>Pergamos</hi> had in her, <hi>thoſe that held the Doctrine of</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam, <hi>and the Doctrine of the</hi> Nicolaitans, <hi>which God bated,</hi> ver. 14.15. Thyatyra <hi>ſuffered that Woman</hi> Jezabel, <hi>which called her ſelfe a Propheteſſe, to teach, and to ſeduce men to commit Fornication, and to Eate of things ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104483:17"/>unto Idolls,</hi> ver. 20. Sardis <hi>had a Name that ſhe lived, but was dead,</hi> Chap. 3.1. Philadelphia <hi>was the pureſt of all the reſt;</hi> yet ſhe is Charged with her defect too, <hi>ſhe had but a little ſtrength,</hi> ver. 8. Laodicea <hi>was neither cold nor hot, but lukewarme;</hi> ſhe had a high and Phariſaicall Conceipt of her ſelf, <hi>that ſhe was Rich, and Wanted no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing;</hi> where our Saviour tells her, <hi>She was Poor, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, and Blinde, and Naked;</hi> and yet notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all this, a Church ſtill; notwithſtanding all theſe Defects, Corruptions, Blemiſhes in all the reſt; yet all this did not un-Church them, all Churches ſtill; <hi>The ſeven Candleſticks are the ſeven Churches; and the ſeven Churches the ſeven Candleſticks;</hi> nay, <hi>Golden Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks</hi> ſtill, for all this. It was not a little Droſſe amongſt them, not a little Duſt, nor Ruſt adhering to them, that made them ceaſe to be Candleſticks; yea, <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Candleſticks</hi> ſtill, for all this: <hi>The ſeven Golden Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticks are the ſeven Churches.</hi> Surely, Chriſt the Lord of the Churches, is more Charitable, more Indulgent to us in this point, then we are one to another. We have a Generation among us, I pray God they be not ſuch a Generation as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.12. <hi>A Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration that it pure in their own Eyes, yet are not clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from their iniquity:</hi> I hope the beſt; But ſuch a Generation we have amongſt us, which out of a high Conceit of their own tranſcendent purity, think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too good to joyne with others; others too bad to be admitted with them into Church-fellowſhip: Where they ſee any Defects, Errors, Miſcarriages, though they be but perſonall, not Congregationall, and ſuch as we doe no way allow of, but reprove, cry out againſt, lament, and bewaile, where we cannot help it; yet theſe
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104483:17"/>men take ſuch offence at them, that they with-draw themſelves, ſeparate from our Congregations, un-church us, revile, reproach, rayle upon us, as Synagogues of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, Lymbes of Anti-Chriſt, and caſt a greater reproach upon us, then the Papiſt, themſelves. But my beloved Brethren, <hi>From what ſpirit comes this?</hi> from that ſpirit and wiſedom which is from above, <hi>which is firſt pure; then peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be intreated? &amp;c.</hi> Or, <hi>from a ſpirit of pride, ſingularity, diſdain, vain glory, and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie?</hi> ſurely theſe things proceed not from that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit which deſcended in the likeneſſe of a Dove, in all meekneſſe and gentleneſſe; but rather that of <hi>Boanerges,</hi> the Sonnes of Thunder, <hi>which called for Lightning and Fire to deſtroy, and to avenge. But if the ſame minde were in you, which was in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> in this Text, you would be more Charitable. He owns the Churches yet <hi>for Candleſtickes:</hi> Nay, for all the Ruſt, and Duſt, and Droſſe which they were Corrupted withall, for <hi>Golden Candleſtickes: The ſeven Golden Candleſtickes are the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But we have-not yet Examined, <hi>Why the Churches are ſet forth unto us under the Name and Notion of Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> It is certain, that in this <hi>ſimile,</hi> the ſpirit of God doth allude to that famous Candleſticke which was ſet up in the Tabernacle, of which we Reade <hi>Exod.</hi> 25.31. From it then we muſt fetch light to underſtand what is meant by comparing the Churches to it. And herein the Apprehenſions of Expoſitors have been very luxuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in taking hold of variety of particulars, from whence
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104483:18"/>to rayſe ſeverall Obſervations, not impertinent, but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially from theſe three things. Firſt, From the Matter and the Mettle whereof they are made. Secondly, From the Forme of them. Thirdly, From the Uſe of them. Friſt, From the Matter and the Mettall of them, thus: When Chriſt reſembles the Churches by <hi>Golden Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtickes,</hi> his meaning is, That they are, <hi>Per ſanctitatem pura, per dona &amp; gratias ſpiritu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſancti pretioſa, per ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceritatem ſolida, per bona opera ſplendentia, per morum gravitatem ponderoſa, per perſecutionem probata, per obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dientiam facilè ductilia, per praedicationem verbi ſonora.</hi> By their holineſſe they are pure, by their Gifts and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they are pretious, by their ſincerity they are ſolid, by their wiſedom and gravity they are weighty, by the fire of temptation and perſecution they are tryed, by the Preaching of the word they ring, and give a ſound, by their charity and obedience they are eaſily drawne forth as Gold out of the Lumpe, into Leafe Gold. All this From the Matter of them, and the Mettle whereof they are made. Secondly, From the Forme of them: It is obſerved, that they are erected, they look upward toward Heaven: ſuch Candleſticks ſhould the Churches be: <hi>Erecta per rerum divinarum contemplationem; Erecta per ſpem &amp; fidem in Chriſto ad dextram Dei in coelo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; Erecta ad lucem celeſtem recipiendam: Erecta ad lucem illam aliis prebendam, &amp; circumquaque commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicandam:</hi> They muſt be Candleſticks erected and tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upward, by their Contemplation of Divine things, and ſetting their Hearts and Minds on the things that are above, erected by Faith and Hope in Chriſt, ſitting at the right Hand of the Father, erected to receive the Heavenly Light from the Father of Lights; and erected,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:104483:18"/>that it being ſet up on high in them, might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the farther be Communicated to others: this from the Forme of the Candleſtickes. Thirdly, From the Uſe of them, and that was touch't in the laſt, to hold forth the Light: <hi>Men doe not light a Candle to put it under a Buſhell, but to ſet up in a Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke, that it may give Light to all that are in the Houſe:</hi> Such a Candleſticke is the Church, to hold forth the Light of Truth to all her Children, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led therefore, <hi>The Pillar of Truth,</hi> Timothy 3.15. becauſe as the Pillar holds forth the Kings Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion fixt upon it, that all that are Concerned in it may take notice of it, and he that runneth may Reade it. So ſhould the Church hold forth the Truth, that it may be viſible and audible to all her Children and Members, as the Pillar doth the Proclamation, the Candleſticke the Light. What uſe is there of the Candleſticke, if there be no Candle ſet up in it? Or what uſe of the Candle, except it be lighted, that it may burne and ſhine? And that it may doe ſo, there are two things neceſſary. Firſt, That it ſhould be fed with a continuall ſupply of Oyle, or other moyſture, to nouriſh it, and to keep it burning; and good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, that they, which like Candles, conſume them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to give light to others, ſhould from others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Oyle and nouriſhment which may keep them burning. Secondly, 'Tis neceſſary ſometimes that they ſhould be Topt, or Snufft: We Reade <hi>Exodus</hi> 25.38. that in the Tabernacle where the Golden Candleſticke was, there were alſo <hi>Snuffers, and Snuffe-diſhes:</hi> What the uſe of thoſe Snuffers was,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:104483:19"/>we all know, and what that uſe of them teacheth and leads to, we may imagine: ſometimes the Candles may burne luxuriouſly, and in that Caſe, 'Tis neceſſary they ſhould be ſnufft: ſometimes they may burne but dimly, being choakt, and darkened with the ſnuffe it ſelfe, and in that Caſe, 'tis fit they ſhould be ſnufft: ſometimes there may be a Theefe in the Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, that may waſte the Oyle and nouriſhment of it, by conveying it the wrong way, and in that Caſe they may not take it ill if they be ſnufft. The Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks themſelves are not ſo free from Ruſt and Duſt, but ſometimes they will ſtand in need of ſcouring, of rubbing, and of dreſſing, by Corrections, Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and wholeſome Diſcipline; Nor doe the Lights in them burne ſo clearly, but they had need to be look't too. Are we of this ſociety ſo innocent, that we need no inſpection? or ſo nocent, that we need to feare a Viſitation? Are we, amongſt all Societies, ſo abſolute, ſo independent, that we have no Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendent? or if any, who ſhould that be, but our Chiefe Prieſt, the Angel of this Church, our Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan, our Metropolitan, whoſe Presbytery we are, and to whom we have all Sworne Canonicall Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? VVho but he our <hi>Aaron,</hi> to fit as a Refiner, to purifie the Sonnes of <hi>Levy</hi> in this Society?</p>
            <p>But we haſte to the other Part of the Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this <hi>Wonderfull Perſon,</hi> as he is here repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to us, <hi>Walking in the midſt of the ſeven Golden Candleſticks.</hi> And this is the laſt Part of this his Deſcription.</p>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:104483:19"/>
            <p> And what is meant by this his <hi>Walking there,</hi> Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> tells us, <hi>Ambulare in medio Candelabrorum, quid eſt, niſi Eccleſiis ſemper adeſſe, eis delectari, eas ſervare, erudire, protegeri, dirigere, juvare, &amp; eis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus modis advigilare:</hi> To walke in the midſt of the Golden Candleſticks, what is it, but to be ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with the Churches, to delight in them, to direct them, to protect them, to inſtruct them, and by all means to Conſult their good? they are all Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in theſe foure; His Preſence with them: His Delight in them: His Obſervation of them: And his Care for them. Firſt, He walks in the midſt of them with Delight; <hi>Of</hi> Syon, he hath ſaid, <hi>here will I dwell, for I have a delight in her;</hi> and ſo he walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the midſt of them, as a Man would doe in his Garden, for Pleaſure, and for Recreation. Secondly, He walks in the midſt of them, to Preſerve them, and Protect them; where he is in the midſt of them within, he is as a VVall of Braſſe round about them without too: Nay, <hi>As a Wall of Fire,</hi> Zachary 2.5. not onely to Defend them within; but to Conſume and burne up all them without, which ſhall preſume to attempt to break in upon them; and ſo he walkes in the midſt of them, as once he did in the midſt of the <hi>Fiery Furnace</hi> for the preſervation of the three Children, <hi>Daniel</hi> 3.23. which he did ſo powerfully, that the fire in it had power to burne the Bands and Cords, with which they were bound; but not to <hi>touch an Haire of their Heads, or a Hemme of their Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Thirdly, He walkes in the midſt of them, <hi>Erudire,</hi> to Teach, and to Inſtruct them, to Awe them,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:104483:20"/>to keep them in order; <hi>For he is the beloved Sonne of the Father, in whom he is well pleaſed, whom we muſt Heare and Obey,</hi> Matthew 3.17. He the great Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of his Church, whom we are Commanded to Heare with a ſevere intimation, <hi>by his Spirit, by his Word, and by his Paſtors ſent out by him,</hi> doth he teach the Churches to the worlds end: And ſo he walks in the midſt of them, as a Schoole-Maſter in the midſt of his Schoole, and his Diſciples or Schollers. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, He walkes in the midſt of them, <hi>To Obſerve them, to take notice of their Carriage, their Manners, their Order, and their Behaviour,</hi> as appeares by the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Charges which he gives to theſe ſeverall Churches in this his Viſitation, in all of them making good what in Generall he tells them, before he come to deale particularly with them, <hi>Novi Opera tua, I know thy Works:</hi> And ſo he walks in the midſt of them, as the Maſter of the Feaſt in the Goſpel walk't in his Dining Roome, to take a View of his Gueſts, to ſee who had, and who had not on his <hi>Wedding Garment.</hi> And to this purpoſe it is obſervable, in what manner of Poſture and Geſture he is here ſeen, He is ſeen <hi>Walking;</hi> Not <hi>Sedet Otioſus,</hi> as <hi>Bullinger</hi> obſerves; not <hi>Stat Negligens,</hi> he doth not ſit, as being Idle; He ſtands not ſtill, as being negligent; but he is ſeen <hi>Walking,</hi> from end to end, forward and backward, to and fro, that at every turne he might take a View, and at every ſtep caſt an Eye, that nothing done or ſaid amongſt them, may eſcape his Cognizance. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he is walking, <hi>in Medio</hi> in the midſt of the Candleſticks; <hi>Non in Angulo, non in exteriori aliquâ
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:104483:20"/>parte;</hi> Not in a Corner, not in ſome Skirt, or Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of them: but, <hi>In medio Candelabrorum,</hi> in the midſt of the Golden Candleſticks, that he might look over them every way; and they at an equall diſtance on all ſides, might receive from him that Direction, Protection, Comfort, and Encouragement which is their Light and Life. The truth is, He bought them, he layd down a Price for them, which was far more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious then Gold, his own Blood; he had need ſee what becomes of them, and he is to deliver them up to God the Father; he received them by weight, and he received them by tale; <hi>Of thoſe which thou haſt given me, have I loſt none;</hi> It is his great Care that he may deliver up his full Tale, and that he may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them up Pure, and Bright, and Cleare, and that he may preſent them without ſpot or wrinkle; and therefore is it that he hath ſuch a ſpeciall Care of them, ſuch a vigilant Eye upon them, continually re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident among them, and walking in the midſt of them. Oh how happy are the Churches under the inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuch an Eye, under the Care of ſuch a Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian, under the Protection of ſuch a Patron, in the Favour of ſuch a Prince, the Teaching of ſuch a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the Interceſſion and Benediction of ſuch a Prieſt continually preſent with them, Preſident over them, and reſident among them, walking in the midſt of them? and how holily ought they to carry themſelves in ſuch a Preſence? how circumſpectly under the Inſpection of ſo ſevere an Eye? that when he ſhall come to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit them, as here he doth this Church, and to take an Account of them, they may give up their Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:104483:21"/>with joy, when he ſhall ſay unto them, as here to <hi>Epheſus, Novi Opera tua, I know thy Works,</hi> they may be ſuch as they need not be aſhamed of, ſuch as may ſtand by us, and abide the tryall, ſuch as may prayſe us in the Gate, ſuch, as upon the enquiry and examination, he may approve of, and upon which we may expect the Promiſe here in this Viſitation made <hi>Vincentibus, To them that over come, to Eate of the Fruit of the Tree of Life, which is in the midſt of the Paradice of God, to Receive the White Stone, and therein the New Name Written, which none can Reade, but he that receiveth it, to be Cloathed with White Ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, waſht in the Blood of the Lambe, and in it to follow the Lambe whither ſoever he goeth, and to be ever in his Preſence, in whoſe Preſence is fulneſſe of joy, and at whoſe Right Hand there is pleaſure for evermore:</hi> Which the Great God of Heaven and Earth be pleaſed to admit us unto, for his ſake which <hi>Holdeth the ſeven Starrs in his Right Hand, and Walketh in the midſt of the ſeven Golden Candleſticks;</hi> To whom be all Honour and Glory, now and for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:104483:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
